<#GAPDoc Label="ChapIntroduction">
  
<Section Label="SecWhyStripsNotStrings">
  <Heading>
    Why "strips", not "strings"?
  </Heading>


  First, some context. Representation theorists use the word <E>string</E> to
  mean a decorated graph that describes a module; fittingly, this module is
  then  dubbed a <E>string module</E>. Liu and Morin <Cite Key="LM04"/> showed
  that the syzygy of a string module over a special biserial (SB) algebra is a
  direct sum of string modules. This means that, in essence, we can forget
  about the modules <E>per se</E> and compute syzygies just at the level of
  strings. Liu and Morin's proof is constructive, specifying how to obtain the
  strings indexing the indecompsoable direct summands of syzygy from thae 
  string indexing the original module. Their language sketches how to spot
  patterns appearing "from one syzygy to the next", but it does not scale in a
  particularly transparent way. For example, I believe it does not lend itself
  to clearly seeing asymptotic behaviour of syzygies of string modules. My
  research has aimed, in part, to provide a more robust language: one which
  lays bare more patterns in the syzygies of string modules over SB algebras
  in a manner amenable to computer calculation.
  <P />

  One key ingredient is a slight refinement of the definition of a string.
  Really, this differs from the established definition only in technical ways,
  the effect being to disambiguate how the graph is decorated so that the
  syzygy calculation is streamlined. In my thesis, I propose the term
  <E>strip</E> for this refined notion of a string. A happy side-effect of
  this name change is that it avoids the clash with what &GAP; already thinks
  "string" means.
  <P />

  <E>
    In brief: if whenever you read the word "strip" here, you imagine that it
    means the kind of decorated graph that representation theorists call a
    "string", then you won't go too far wrong.
  </E>
  <P />
</Section>

<Section>
  <Heading>
    Aims
  </Heading>

  Some text to go here!
</Section>

<Section>
  <Heading>
    Installation
  </Heading>
  
  Some text to go here!
</Section>
<#/GAPDoc>