<#GAPDoc Label="TitlePage">

<Title>
  &PACKAGENAME;
</Title>

<Version>
  Version &VERSION;
</Version>

<TitleComment>
  A discrete model of special biserial algebras, string modules and their
  syzygies
</TitleComment>

<Author>
  Joe Allen (he/him/his)
</Author>

<Abstract>
  String modules for special biserial (SB) algebras are represented by string
  graphs. Many modules related to a given string module, including its
  syzygy, transpose and vector-space dual and hence Auslander-Reiten translate
  and inverse translate, are also string modules. These related modules can be
  calculated combinatorially rather than algebraically. &PACKAGENAME;
  implements this functionality in &GAP;, representing string graphs as objects
  called <E>strips</E>. It includes some tests for associated properties such
  as syzygy type, delooping level and weak periodicity.
  <P />
  
  &PACKAGENAME; also includes bookkeeping functionality for multisets, which it
  calls <E>collected lists</E>, and it integrates with (and depends on) the
  &QPA; package for quiver algebras and their modules.
  <!--
  The syzygy of a string module (over an SB algebra) is a direct sum of
  string modules, by a 2004 result of Liu and Morin, therefore syzygy-taking
  can be performed at the (combinatorial) level of string graphs rather than
  the (homological-algebraic) level of modules.
  <P />
  
  This package represents string graphs in &GAP; by objects called strips and
  it implements syzygy-taking as an operation on them. Together with some small
  utilities for book-keeping, it allows for very efficient calculation of
  <M>k</M>th syzygyies for large <M>k</M>.
  <P />
  
  We also include functionalities for the dual, transpose and delooping
  level of a strip.
  -->
</Abstract>

<Copyright>
  &copyright; 2020-2021 Joe Allen
</Copyright>


<Acknowledgements>
  I thank my fellow members of "Team Splendid" -- Prof Jeremy Rickard, Dr Simon
  Peacock, Charley Cummings and Luke Kershaw -- for countless engaging
  conversations about representation theory, programming and much else besides.
  In particular I thank my PhD supervisor Jeremy, on whom I inflicted multiple
  early iterations of &PACKAGENAME;, for his time and comments and my "big
  brother" Simon for helping me organise the &PACKAGENAME; website. This
  package was much worse before their feedback.
  <P />
  
  Additionally, I received help understanding <Package>GAPDoc</Package> from
  Prof Max Horn and Dr Frank Lübeck, the latter of whom wrote the
  <F>makedocrel.g</F> file included in this package. I am grateful to them
  both.
</Acknowledgements>

<Colophon>
  This package was created during the author's doctoral studies at the
  University of Bristol.
</Colophon>
<#/GAPDoc>